Register of the Georges Scapini Papers, 1928-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Georges Scapini Papers,
1928-1976
78011
Scapini, Georges, 1893-1976
27 manuscript boxes, 2 album boxes 13.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, legal documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to French politics, French prisoners of war in Germany during World War II, and the trial of Georges Scapini as a Nazi collaborator, 1952
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Prisoners of war; War crime trials; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Collaborationists; World War, 1939-1945--France; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons; France; France--Foreign relations--Germany; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945; France--Politics and government--1914-1940; Germany; Germany--Foreign relations--France; Diplomats--France
Biographical Note
Georges Scapini
1893, October 4 Born in Paris, France
1914-1918 Wounded in combat, lost eyesight
1928-1940 Deputy, National Assembly
1940-1944 Ambassador to Germany, Chief of the Diplomatic Service for Prisoners of War
1944, December Arrested by the German authorities, having refused to serve the French government in Sigmaringen, Germany
1945, May Incarcerated by the French authorities for intelligence with the enemy; released after 10 months
1949 Tried in absentia; sentenced to 5 years of hard labor
1952 Tried by a military tribunal; acquitted
1960 Author, Mission sans Gloire 1928, L'apprentissage de la nuit 1928, A Challenge to Darkness 1929 Translated with an Introduction by Helen Keller
1976, March 25 Died in Cannes, France
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1934-1976. (Box Box No. 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1936-1960. (Box Box No. 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1928-1976. (Box Box No. 2-23.)
  Correspondence, legal documents, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, printed matter, reports, studies, arranged alphabetically by topic.
- Printed Matter, 1941-1948. (Box Box No. 24.)
  Newspapers
- Audio-Visual File, 1940-1944. Albums of photographs (Box fA-B.)
- 1981 Increment (Box Box No. 25-27)
Container List
- Correspondence, 1934-1976
  - General, 1940-1964 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, n.d.
  - Abetz, Otto, 1934-1941
  - Anderson, Paul B., 1941
  - L'Assistance Publique (Public Relief Administration), Paris, 1942
  - Berthon, André, 1953
  - Borotra, Jean, 1976
  - Bridoux, General, 1944
  - Brinon, Ferdinand de, 1941-1944
  - Brissaud, André
  - Cabinet du Maréchal Pétain (Office of Marshal Pétain), 1941-1944
  - Ciret, René and Alice, 1942
  - Consulate of Sweden, Paris, n.d.
  - Darlan, Admiral, 1941
  - Demaria, 1940
  - Dobler, Jean, 1937
  - Duveau, Maurice, 1941
  - L'Estoile, Maurice de, 1952
  - Eugène, Michel, 1941
  - Fayard, Jean, 1938
  - Le Figaro, Paris, 1960
  - Genevoix, René and Maurice, 1970
  - German Embassy, Paris, 1940-1942
  - Gaumont Raymond, Mrs. I, 1940
  - Gil de Lobo, María Fca., 1971
  - Giot, J., 1950
  - Humann, Colonel von, 1941-1943
  - Huntziger, General, 1940-1941
  - Jourdain, M., 1939
  - Kagen, D., 1940
  - Lafaye, Louis, 1953
  - Laureux, Marguerite, 1950-1975
  - Laureux, Pierre, 1948-1962
  - Laval, Pierre, 1940-1944
  - Lyautey, Mrs., 1943
  - Merle, Renée, 1946
  - Ministère des Affaires Etrangères, Paris (Ministry of Foreign Relations), 1949-1959
  - Mouttel, Countess Auguste de, 1940
  - Nosek, 1940-1943
  - Patterson, Jefferson, 1940
  - Pétain, Marshal, 1940-1944
  - Reinecke, General, 1940-1943
  - Renaud, Lévy, 1941
  - Rodhain, Jean, 1946-1949
  - Roehrig, 1941-1943
  - Schleier, Consul General, Paris, 1940-1941
  - Silva, Georges, n.d.
  - Simon, Paul, 1940
  - Tourneur de Marçay, Georgette Le, 1940
  - Turkey, The Ambassador of, Paris, 1946
  - Weiland, Jean, 1940
- Speeches and Writings, 1936-1960
  - Account of camp inspections, n.d., One typescript of an article (Box 1)
  - Les Dessous de l'Importation des Viandes (The Seamy Side of Meat Imports), 1939., One typescript of an essay
  - Mission sans Gloire (Mission without Glory), Paris, 1960
    - Advertisements, reviews
    - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Documents (photocopies) - Appendices of Mission sans Gloire
  - Note sur la Situation Franco-Allemande à la date du 4 Septembre 1938 (Note on the Franco-German situation under date of September 4, 1938), 1938., One typescript of a memorandum
  - Petite histoire personnelle qui facilite la compréhension d'une période qui s'é tend de 1940 à la fin de la vie, de la mienne tout au moins (Short personal story which helps understand a period of time stretching from 1940 to the end of life, at least of mine), n.d., One typescript of an essay
  - Remarks, National Assembly, Paris, n.d. One typewritten copy of his comments on the German reoccupation of Rhenany, reprinted in Le Petit Bleu, Paris, March 12, 1936
  - Speech, Annales Coloniales (Colonial Records), n.d. One printed copy of his speech reprinted in the Dépche Coloniale Belge, Bruxelles, February 5, 1938
  - Speech, Dinner given by the Saint-Gobain Company in honor of some employeès released from German camps, November 13, 1941., One typewritten copy
- Subject File, 1928-1978
  - L'Aéciste, Paris, August 1970 (Box 2)
  - L'Alerte, Nice, 1940-1942
  - Allemagne, Paris, April-May 1949
  - Algeria
  - Ambrière, Francis (Charles-Louis Letellier)
  - Arrivets, Charles
  - The Aulois affair
  - Bergery, Gaston
  - Blum, Léon
  - Boissarie, André
  - Brinon, Ferdinand de
  - Canal Saint-Quentin
  - Chambrun, Josée Laval de
  - Chambrun, René de
  - Churchill, Winston
  - Comité France-Allemagne (France-Germany Committee), 1934-1938
  - Le Crapouillot, Paris, 1968-1974
  - Darlan, Admiral
  - Déat, Marcel
  - Desouches, Jean
  - Devaux, Louis
  - Dewerse, Lucien
  - Duclos, Jacques
  - Faure, Paul
  - Flandin, Pierre-Etienne
  - France
    - Colonialism. De la Nation de cent millions d'hommes à l'Empire de cent millions d'ames, Paris, n.d.
    - Domestic policy (Box 3)
      - General, 1940-1971
      - Communist party
      - Le Front de la Paix (The Peace Front)
      - May 68
      - Socialist party
      - Vichy
        - General
        - Armistice
          - Commission (Wiesbaden)
          - Convention, legal aspects of
        - High Court of Justice, Paris, trial of Vichy officials, 1945
        - Paxton, Robert O., La France de Vichy, 1940-1944, Paris, 1973, including reviews and Scapini's remarks
    - Foreign policy
      - General, 1965-1967
      - Embassy in Berlin. For bombing of November 1943, see also CORRESPONDENCE, Laval
      - Great Britain, 1936-1968
      - Morocco, 1955
      - Soviet-Union. Treaty of 1935
      - Vietnàm, 1947-1949
    - History
  - Garibaldi, Sante
  - Gaulle, Charles de. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Laureux (January 8, 1959) General file
    - Newspaper articles (Box 4)
  - Germany
    - Foreign policy
      - General, 1938
      - France, 1938-1944
      - Great Britain, 1938-1944
      - Soviet-Union. Non-aggression pact of 1939
    - Völkischer Beobachter, Munich, April 9/10, 1944
  - Giraud, General Henri-Honoré
  - Guibert, Lieutenant-Colonel
  - Herriot, Edouard
  - Hitler, Adolf
    - General
    - Interview with Leni Riefenstahl, February 24, 1936
    - Meeting with Mussolini, March 19, 1940
    - Meeting with Scapini, April 15, 1935
    - Speech at the Reichstag, January 30, 1939
  - International affairs, 1938-1960
  - International Committee of the Red Cross
    - Chenevière, Jacques, L'Action de la Croix-Rouge pendant la Guerre (The Activity of the Red Cross during the War), Paris, June 1946
    - Meeting with Scapini, April 21, 1944
    - Reports of camp inspections
  - Isorni, Jacques (Box 5)
  - Jouhaud, General
  - La Journée du 6 Février, Georges Imann, Paris, 1934
  - Juin, General Alphonse. See Le Monde et la Vie
  - Kerillis, Henri de
  - Korean War
  - Lattre de Tassigny, Jean de. See Le Monde et la Vie
  - Laureux, Marguerite - CORRESPONDENCE
    - General (mostly concerning the Stalag IA Association in Bordeaux, France), 1941
    - Mrs. Didelet, 1942-1943
  - Laureux, Pierre. See also Ambrière, Francis; Prisoners of war, French, Camps, Oflag XB, friendly society of, 1947-1948; Prisoners of war, French, Camps, Stalag IA; Prisoners of war, French, Escapes; Prisoners of war, French, Service Diplomatique des Prisonniers de Guerre; Delegation in Berlin, Accounting; Prisoners of war, French, Service Diplomatique des Prisonniers de Guerre, Delegation in Berlin, Final months and end of Scapini's mission; Prisonners of war, German (in France); Rodhain, Jean; Scapini, Georges, Trial, First, 1949
    - CORRESPONDENCE, 1943-1962
    - File on Bernard, Godard and Hélié
    - Légion Tricolore (controversy brought up by Le Front des Barbelés
    - Letters to the editor
    - Message to the prisoners of war, November 23, 1942
    - Miscellaneous
    - Notes on the Geneva Convention on Prisoners of War
    - Obituaries, January 21, 1974
    - Trial, 1945-1946
      - Bibliographical notes for Rault, Laureux's lawyer
      - CORRESPONDENCE
        - with, or of, his family, May-June 1945
        - Rault, 1945-1946
        - Requests of testimonies, and replies (addressed either to Laureux or Virenque, his lawyer), 1945-1946
        - Sympathy and congratulations letters, 1945-1946
        - Virenque, 1946
      - Costs
      - Defense pleas file (including a reply to Durandin's deposition, questions to be asked, etc.)
      - Investigation
        - Answer to the Commission's report
        - Depositions (Charrier, Durandin, Fauchas, Guillaume, Jacomet, Janot, Laureux, Mazet)
      - Legislation regarding collaboration and national indignity (Box 6)
      - Memoranda of his activity at Stablack
      - Miscellaneous
      - Note by Rault for the examining magistrate
      - Officer candidates file (including CORRESPONDENCE with Janot and Jacomet)
      - Press accounts
      - Report to the Minister of War, September 7, 1945
      - Testimonies (letters sent to Virenque)
      - Verdict
  - Laval, Pierre
  - Légion des Volontaires Français (Legion of French Volunteers)
  - Lunebourg - Massacre of nearly 250 prisoners of war, mostly French
  - Man, Henri de
  - Marxism
  - Mauriac, François
  - Minute, Paris, 1968
  - Mitterrand, François
  - Le Monde et la Vie, Paris, February and March 1965
  - Mussolini, Benito
  - Nuremberg trial
    - General
    - Keitel (Scapini's testimony)
    - Reinecke (Scapini's testimony)
  - L'Opinion Indépendante du Sud-Ouest, Agen, 1963-1974 (Box 7)
  - Paris Match, Paris, April 1966
  - Pétain, Philippe
    - General
    - Funeral oration by the Cardinal Segura, Spain, August 8, 1951
    - Le Maréchal, Paris, 1965-1974
    - Messages
    - Trial - Revision
    - Trips through France
  - Prisoners of war, French (in Germany) (Box 8)
    - Camps
      - Albums and souvenirs given to Scapini
      - Cultural activities
      - Education
      - Education (Box 9)
      - Food distribution
      - Friendly societies
      - Inspections - Reports
        - General
        - Oflags (officers' camps)
        - Stalags (troups' camps), including Frontstalags
      - Maps of camp locations and miscellaneous figures and statistics
      - Medical and sanitary questions
      - Oflag XB
        - Friendly society of
        - Life in
      - Press. See Cultural activities
      - Propaganda
      - Regulations and living conditions (Box 10)
      - Stalag IA at Stablack (officer candidates' camp)
        - General
        - Association in Bordeaux, France
      - Stalag VC
      - Le Stalag XVIII C Vous Parle, October 1943
      - Stalags 325 (Rawa-Ruska) and 369 (Kobierczyn)
    - Centre d'Entr'Aide aux Etudiants Mobilisés et Prisonniers (Relief Center for Mobilized Students and Prisonners)
      - General
      - Cahier de Documentation de la France d'Outre-Mer, Paris, 1944
      - Premier Cahier de Documentation des Ingénieurs et Cadres, Paris, 1942
    - Chaplaincy
    - Commissariat au Reclassement des Prisonniers de Guerre Rapatriés (Commissioner's Office for the Reemployment of the Repatriated Prisoners of war)
    - Escapes
    - Families in France
    - Geneva Convention on Prisoners of War
      - Bretonnière, Maurice, L'Application de la Convention de Genève aux Prisonniers Français en Allemagne durant la Seconde Guerre Mondiale, Paris, May 21, 1949 (thesis)
      - Text, July 27, 1929 (Box 11)
    - Guide du Prisonnier, Paris, November 1943
    - Hommes de Confiance (Confidence Men). See also Toute la France, Articles published in
      - General (mostly CORRESPONDENCE with Scapini)
      - 2 albums of letters to Scapini (mostly season's greetings)
      - Mémento de l'Homme de Confiance, Stalag II D, 1943
    - Jews
    - Labor
      - General
      - Non-commissioned officers
      - Officers
      - in war factories, including protection against aerial bombings
    - Letters addressed to Scapini, 1940-1943 (Box 12)
    - Magazines
    - Ministère des Prisonniers, Déportés et Réfugiés (Ministry of Prisoners, Deported and Refugees)
      - General
      - Bilan d'un Effort, Paris, 1945
    - Mouvement National des Prisonniers de Guerre et des Déportés. Organisation de la Résistance Nationale (National Movement of the Prisoners of War and Deported. Organization of the National Resistance)
    - Officiers-Conseils (Counsel Officers). See also Desouches, Jean
    - Protocole signed between France and Germany regarding prisoners of war, November 16, 1940
    - Red Cross
    - Release of prisoners
      - General
      - German file
      - Reception in France
      - Requests addressed to Scapini (mostly from families). See also Service Diplomatique des Prisonniers de Guerre, File of cases to examine
        - General
        - on health and humanitarian grounds (Box 13)
      - Thank-you letters from prisoners and families under the program called La Relève, (2 folders)
    - Service Diplomatique des Prisonniers de Guerre (Diplomatic Service for Prisoners of War)
      - Administration
      - Delegation in Berlin
        - Accounting - Reports of Laureux
        - CORRESPONDENCE with the Paris Bureau, 1941-1942, including a memorandum entitled Collaboration, June 21, 1941, (3 folders) (Box 14)
        - Final months and end of Scapini's mission
        - Judicial Department
        - Meetings (Box 15)
          - with the Oberkommando of the Wehrmacht, 1940-1944
          - with Reinecke, 1941-1944, (2 folders)
      - File of cases to examine, (2 folders)
      - Paris Bureau (Box 16)
        - Desbons (head) - Report
        - General file
        - Intervention - Nominative list
        - Medical Office - Reports, 1941-1943
        - Memoranda, 1940-1941
        - Notes for Scapini for his camp visits, 1944
        - Press releases
          - General
          - Répertoire des Communiqués Officiels, 1943
        - Survey of the negociations between France and Germany on the subject of prisoners of war, under date of May 1, 1942 (Box 17)
      - Vehicles
    - Statistics
    - Veterans
      - General
      - CORRESPONDENCE with Scapini, 1940-1941
      - Post-war reunions, meetings, congresses, etc.
  - Prisoners of War, French (in the Soviet Union)
  - Prisoners of War, French (in Switzerland)
  - Prisoners of War, German (in France and Berlin)
  - Radio broadcasts
  - Religion
  - Rémy, Colonel
  - Rivarol, Paris, 1961-1967
  - Rodhain, Jean. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Laureux, November 25, 1962
  - The Scaffa affair
  - Scapini, Georges
    - Appointments, 1941-1944
    - Assistance to various individuals. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Abetz; Brinon; Cabinet du Maréchal Pétain; Laval; Nosek; Roehrig; Schleier
      - General, 1940-1944
      - Financial, 1941-1945 (Box 18)
      - to Jews, 1941-1947
    - Deputy, National Assembly
    - Invitations
    - Miscellaneous
    - Trial
      - First, 1949
        - Appeal
        - CORRESPONDENCE (mostly requests of testimonies), 1947-1949
        - Defense memoranda
          - General
          - General, (3 folders) (Box 19)
          - in answer to the report of the Ministère des Anciens Combattants et Victimes de Guerre (Ministry of Veterans and War Victims); report included
        - Investigation (Box 20)
          - Commission's report
          - Depositions. See also Comité France-Allemagne
            - for the defense
            - for the prosecution
            - Scapini
          - Inventory of documents
          - Request for a suspension introduced by Lamouche, Scapini's lawyer
        - Laureux's papers
        - Press accounts
        - Proceedings
          - Dec. 19 (the President's statement and Mrs. Scapini's deposition)
          - Dec. 20 (indictment and verdict)
        - Prosecution's statement
        - Testimonies (Box 21)
          - General (mostly letters sent to Lamouche)
          - Hommes de Confiance and Officiers-Conseils (letters sent to Druon)
      - Second, 1952
        - CORRESPONDENCE (mostly letters of sympathy and congratulations) 1952
        - Defense memorandum
        - Documents (photocopies)
        - Lamouche's papers
        - Press accounts
        - Proccedings, July 23-24 (Box 22)
          - Defense
            - Pleas of lawyers Lamouche and Weil
            - Witnesses
          - Indictment
          - Interrogation of Scapini
          - Prosecution's witnesses
          - Verdict
        - Testimonies (letters sent to Lamouche). See also Garibaldi, Sante
  - Soviet Union
    - General
    - L'U.R.S.S. a son 14e Anniversaire. Faits et Chiffres, Paris, 1932
  - Toute la France, Paris
    - General
    - Articles published in
  - Ukrainians, émigrés
  - Union des Aveugles de Guerre (Association of the Blind from War), 1941-1976
  - United States
    - General
    - Report of Jefferson Patterson, U.S. Embassy, Berlin, 1940
  - Veterans
    - General
    - Comite 1939-1940 (Committee 1939-1940), 1941-1943
    - Parliamentary Group, 1939-1940
  - Weygand, General Maxime. See also Le Monde et la Vie
    - General file
    - Letter from Laureux concerning Scapini, 1950
    - Speech given before the officers of the three branches of the army, Dakar, October 20, 1940
  - World War I
  - World War, 1939-1945 (Box 23)
- Printed Matter, 1941-1948
  - Newspapers (Box 24)
- 1981 Increment
  - Additional material on French prisoners of war in German camps (Box 25-27)